Alan Guedes — C.V. ☑ a.guedes@ucl.ac.uk • ③ alanlivio .github.io ③ alanlivio ③ alanlivio

Shorbio

I am a Computer Scientist (Ph.D. & Postdoc) interested in Machine Learning (ML) methods for the next generation of immersive systems and graph-based data. My career can be seen threefold. In research, I worked on research Multimedia & ML projects, contributed to communities (Springer, ACM SIGMM, and SBC WebMedia), and have been awarded research funding. In teaching, I co-supervised students, acted as a lecturer on under- and post-graduate courses, and organized workshops to promote student interest in public engagement. In industry, I added value to it through open source and standards in TV forums (ITU-T SG16 and BR TV Forum). ¹

Experiences

Work

UCL, LASP Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML project

2021-today

Highlights: ACM SIGMM committees and workshop organizer; co-supervised undergrad students.

- SpheryStream project funded by EPSRC to Improve 360-video streaming with profile-based methods

PUC-Rio. TeleMidia Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML & Multimedia projects

2017-2020

Highlights: project PI; team leader; standards contributions; SBC WebMedia committees and workshop organizer (students for social impact); co-supervised under/postgrad students; postgraduate lecturer assistant.

- VideoMR project, funded by Microsoft & RNP to detect inappropriate content in video scenes;
- AML (Anti-Money Laundry) project, funded by BTG Bank, to detect financial transactions risk and anomaly detection;
- GT-RAP project, funded by RNP, to develop a blockchain-based system for academic certificates.

Dynavideo, TV Division

Software engineer
Highlights: multiple awarded social impact projects.

2012-2013

- Brasil4D project, funded by World Bank, to transmit interactive TV content with social features to low-income families. Its results were published in a public report

Education

PUC-Rio

Ph.D. in Informatics. Thesis on Multimodal-multiuser support in multimedia scene descriptions 2013–2017 Highlights: thesis concepts used in SBTVD standard; industry committees.

- PUC-Rio Ginga, funded by PUC-Rio Software Licenses, to develop a reference implementation for TV manufacturers;
- SBTVD Conformance Test Suite project, funded by Brazilian Ministry of Science and Technology, to be used by TV manufacturers

UFPB

MSc. in Informatics. Thesis on Multi-device support in TV app stores

2010-2012

Highlights: thesis concepts used in the awarded Brasil4D project; undergraduate lecturer; project leader

- ${\sf GingaStore},$ funded by RNP, to design a broadband system to deliver TV applications;
- Art TVDI, funded by RNP, to design agile methods for TV applications development;

HEPR

BSc. in Computer Science. Final report on Component-based architecture for TV middleware

2005-2009

- Ginga CDN, funded by RNP, to develop reusable TV middleware components.
- Tutor on Analysis and design of Algorithms;
- Part-Time software developer at Dynavideo TV Division to prototype TV software in ST boards.

¹See certificates at https://alanlivio.github.io/certificates.pdf

Research

Publications	
Google Scholar shows 40+ published papers, 100+ citations, h-index 6.	See below recent and some selected
publications. Elsevier Book Chapter	2022
ACM Multimedia Systems.	2022
Springer Journal on Multimedia Tools and Applications.	2016, 2020
IEEE Symposium on Multimedia (ISM).	2020
• • •	2020, 2020, 2020, 2021, 2021, 2021
ACM Symposium on Document Engineering.	2019
IEEE Multimedia Signal Processing.	2019
Funding	
Microsoft Grant	
Approved as PI in VideoMR project	2019
Committees	
ACM, Special Interest Group on Multimedia	
Reviewer and chairing	2020-today
 Multimedia conference: reviewer (2022), area chair (2022), reproducibility of Multimedia Systems (ACM MM): MMVE review (2021, 2022, 2023) and definition of Limiting Experiences (ACM IMX) conference: reviewer (2022) and area of QoMex conference (ACM QoMEX): reviewer (2023) 	emo chair (2022)
BR Computing Society (SBC), Web&Mulimedia Committee	
Steering Committee	2021-today
Reviewer and chairing - WebMedia conference reviewer (2017-today), chair of Undergrad worksho (2019-2022), and chair of Social Impact Workshop (2019-2022)	<i>2017-toda</i> y op (2018), chair of Demos Workshop
Springer	2022
Reviewer - Journal of Multimedia Tools and Applications: reviewer (2022, 2023) - Iberoamerican Conference on TV Applications and Usability: reviewer (2020)	<i>2022-toda</i> y 0, 2021, 2022)
Brazilian TV Forum (SBTVD)	,
Academic member at Technical Module contributing to TV middleware	standards 2017-2021
International Telecommunication Union (ITU)	
Academic member at SG-16/Q13 contributing to IPTV middleware star	ndards 2017-2021
Training	
UCL : Research Supervision; People Management Essentials; Fundamenta Protection.	Is in Research Funding; GDPR; Data
Nature MasterClass: Narrative Tools for Researchers; Focus on Peer F	Review.
Teaching	
UCL	
Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.	2022-today
SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.	2018-2022
PUC-Rio	
Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (30+)	2019
Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (30 $+$).	2013
Japan International Cooperation Agency	
Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American cour	ntries professionals (30+) 2012

RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (30+)	2011
UFPB	2010
Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (15+)	2010
Training	
UCL: Personal Tutoring; Diversity and Inclusion; Connected Learning Essentials	
LinkdinLearning: Moodle 3.9.	
wards	
ACM	
SIGMM Travel Award for MMSys	2022
SIGHI Gary Marsden Travel Award for IMX	2022
SIGWeb Travel Award for DocEng	2019
Multiple TV associations	
FRIDA Innovative TV technological solutions award for Brasil4D project	2014
SET Conference award on Best TV interactivity solution for Brasil4D project	2013
PremioTV on Innovation and Creativity for Brasil4D project	2013
ITU	

Academic: Execute research agenda. Scientific and standard writing.

IPTV Application Challenge User-friendliness for GingaStore project

Teaching: Course design. Presentation skills.

Programing: Python, TensorFlow, Bash, C++, Lua, Java, JavaScript, Latex, Docker.

Social: Good and empathic communication. Positive, make-it-happen, teamwork, lead-by-example attitudes.

Languages: Portuguese (mother tongue), English (fluent), and Spanish (fluent).

References

Skills

- Laura Toni, I.toni@ucl.ac.uk. Postdoc supervisor at UCL.
- Simone Barbosa, simone@inf.puc-rio.br. Ph.D. supervisor at PUC-Rio.
- Marcelo Moreno, moreno@ice.ufjf.br. ITU SG-16/Q13 and SBTVD collaborator.
- Roberto Azevedo, roberto.azevedo@disneyresearch.com. TeleMidia collaborator.

2012